David Singleton

david@**dsingleton.co.uk** / 07816633410 38 Beryl Road, Hammersmith, W6 8JT

Technical Expertise

Server Side

Extensive working knowledge of **PHP** and **MySQL** – Two years commercial experience of building database driven sites on **LAMP** systems. Advocate for the importance for separation of content from logic and the use of **MVC** structure.

Experience using the **PEAR** library and **Smarty** templating system. Comfortable working with **Web Services** and **APIs**.

Strong interest in **Web Security** issues, in particular the process behind, and prevention of, **Cross Site Scripting** and **Cross Site Request Forgery** attacks.

Some experience working with **Java** Servlets/JSP and Tomcat for web applications and **Ruby** for simple scripting.

Client Side

Expert knowledge of **HTML** and **CSS**. To build semantically coded HTML and tame browser quirks in CSS to produce flexible sites that work in a variety of browsers.

Good working knowledge of **Javascript**, **AJAX** and **Unobtrusive** techniques, to allow pages to function without Javascript. Strong understanding of practical use of **XML**, **XSLT** and **DOM** manipulation.

Strong advocate for the importance of **Web Standards**, **Accessibility** and **Progressive Enhancement** techniques. Interested in the **Semantic Web**, **Microformats** and **Machine Tagging**.

Systems

Comfortable working with **OS X**, **Windows** and **Linux** systems, including Debian and Red Hat.

Good working knowledge of the **unix command line** for basic server administration. Familiar with **Apache**, **httpd.conf** and **.htaccess** files, able to install and configure from scratch.

Work Experience

Spring Digital – Senior Web Developer (Aug 2005 – Current)

30 person Web Design Agency in West London – http://springdigital.co.uk

Main role was **PHP/MySQL developer**, but also did front end development. Capable of switching between roles easily.

Built custom **PHP/MySQL** website. Including basic E-commerce, Recruitment, Mecical Surveys and website for a Savile Row tailor where you can create a full customisable shirt. Developed standard **re-usable** code templates used by the entire development team.

Ran code reviews within the development team to improve code quality and security. Trained

other developers and documented best practice and **coding standards**.

Converting **Photoshop/Fireworks** designs into valid, **semantic** and **accessible** XHTML/CSS web pages. Included the use, and introduction, of **Progressive Enhancement** techniques and unobtrusive Javascript/AJAX.

PHP developer in a **2 man team** building a **OpenLazlo** web application to manage DVD Libraries. The flash communicated with the back-end system through a **RESTful API** and XML responses. Also interacting with the **Amazon API** to gather movie information and artwork.

Built and maintained an internal web application for **18 months**; Used to monitor project progress, **time tracking**, produced complex reports and **invoices**. Central to the day to day management of the company and used daily by ~20 people.

Worked with designers to improve the accessibility and usability of designs and teach HTML/CSS.

PureFM.com – Web Designer (Dec 2004 – Jul 2005)

University of Portsmouth Student Radio Station.

Took the role of front end developer/designer as part of a small **5 person team** creating a brand new station website. Also included setting up a dedicated server as a web server and provide streaming audio for internet broadcasts.

Ran a weekly radio show with another student, playing and promoting music we were passionate about.

FFGurus.net - Web Developer (Aug 2000 - Sep 2003)

A large gaming website, with high traffic and a busy community

Unpaid work as an administrator – Responsibilities included developing dynamic content (in PHP/MySQL), a complete HTML re-design, **managing the community** and **developing new features** of the site.

Education

University of Portsmouth (Sep 2002 – Jun 2005)

Studying **Internet Technology** BSc achieving a **First Class** degree with honours.

Course Covered

- Network Administration
- Internet Applications
- Network Design & Security
- Software Systems

- System Security
- Distributed Systems
- Multimedia Networks
- Advanced Web Programming

Final Year Project

Developed a web based system to manage and syndicate news for the my University department. **Multiple levels** of users could use the system to manage news items, which were then available via the web and syndicated with **RSS** and **ATOM**.

Built around a LAMP server with a custom framework written in **Object Oriented** PHP, based on an **MVC architecture**, using **Smarty** and **Mod Rewrite** to generate **Clean URLs**.